Guide to the Cyrus Adler Papers (includes Shorewalkers) 1952-2011 MS 3
New-York Historical Society
- Series IV: Shorewalkers, 1968-2011
  - Subseries IV.2: Newsletters and Press Releases
    - Shorewalker News and Press Releases, 1982-2006 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 7)
  - Subseries IV.3: Events and Promotional Materials, 1999-2006
    - Brochures and Fliers, 2001-2004 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 8)
      This folder contains fliers promoting the creation of the Grand Harlem River Park, budget breakdown of the Batt to Bear Walk, and promotion of the Great Saunter.
    - Ephemera: T-Shirt and Buttons, c 1990s (Offsite-box 9, Folder 9)
    - Map of Harlem River Valley, 2005 (Oversize Medium, Folder Adler OS1)
      This map was published by Shorewalkers and lists places of interest that dot the Harlem River Valley. Also includes a brochure, "Harlem River Valley Map & Guide."
    - Shorewalkers Logo Contests, 2004 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 10)
      This folder contains correspondence and financial statements relating to the creation of the logo for the Batt to Bear and Great Saunter trails. Of note is a list of New York schools considered for the logo contest. Winners were awarded $250, print samples, and credit in the Shorewalkers' website and newsletter.
    - Shorewalkers Beach Clean-Up, 2000 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 11)
    - Shorewalkers "Festooning Manhattan's Rim: The Great New York Island 32-Mile Necklace", 1999, 2006 (Oversize Medium, Folder Adler OS2)
      This folder contains posters, subway maps, and other literature promoting a community project to celebrate Manhattan's shore parks and promenades.
    - Topographic Maps Order Forms, 1987 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 12)
    - The Great Saunter Program Guide, 2006 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 13)
      This folder contains literature and program guides for The Great Saunter of 2006--the 21st Annual exploration around Manhattan's rim.
    - The Great Saunter: A 32-Mile Walk Around Manhattan, 1996 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 14)
      This folder contains a small photo journal created by Graeme Birchall, a member of Shorewalkers, Inc. It provides an account of the 1996 Great Saunter from its starting point on Fulton Street in Lower Manhattan, several of of the markers along the Manhattan shore, until its final stop at the South Street Seaport. Photographs taken by Birchall complement the description provided.
    - The Great Saunter Banner, 2006 (Offsite-box 18)
      This rolled banner is large and somewhat fragile.
  - Subseries IV.4: Publications, 19xx-19xx; 0.01 Linear feet
    This subseries includes Cyrus Adler's 1997 guide to walking the Hudson River Shore Trail, along with various environmental studies and impact statements for walkways in the tri-state area.
    - Walking the Hudson, Batt to Bear: From the Battery to Bear Mountain, by Cyrus Adler, 1997 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 1)
      This book was written by Cyrus Adler and is the first complete guide to walking the Hudson River Shore Trail north to Bear Mountain from Battery Park in lower Manhattan. This trail was scouted by Cy Adler and fellow Shorewalkers in the 1980s and 1990s.
    - Where the Pavement Ends: The Open Space Imperative, 1987 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 2)
      This report on land use in the tri-state region between 1964 and 1985 was published by Regional Plan Association.
    - Building Greenways in the Hudson River Valley, 1989-1990 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 3)
      This folder also contains A Cross Jersey Trail and Greenway prepared for Columbia Gas Transmission Company.
    - Hudson River Estuary Management Plan and Draft Generic Environmental Impact Statement-Executive Summary, 1990 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 4)
      This Executive Summary represented the initial efforts of the Department of Environmental Conservation (DEC) to identify principal Hudson River Estuary management needs. Also included is an annoucement of a Public Hearing Notice for the Draft Management Plan and Environmental Impact Statement for the Hudson River Estuary.
    - Patriots' Path: A Red, White and Blue Greenway, 1975 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 4)
      In addition to the article, Patriots' Path: A Red, White and Blue Greenway, the folder contains a river corridor study of Morris County, New Jersey published in 1975, which mapped out the Partriots' Path Trail.
    - Cross Jersey Trail and Greenway, 1990 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 6)
      This booklet provides historical background and photos for the 16 historic houses maintained by the New York Department of Parks and Recreation and the Historic House Trust.
  - Subseries IV.5.: Photographs
    Arrangement
    These photographic materials were originally housed in brown envelopes that included photographic prints, negatives, and in some cases, handwritten notes. Each envelope is numbered; Adler used a numbering system that appears to be based on the year and month the photos were taken. Photographs are arranged chronologically using Adler's numbering system, rather than by subject.
    For preservation purposes, photos and negatives have been removed from their orginal envelopes and are housed separately in acid-free envelopes. Photographs are boxed separately from negatives. Some of the negatives in the collection were not printed, so researchers should consult both photograph and negative boxes for a complete set of images.
    There are also two folders of negatives from the 1990's that are separately housed in Box 10 because of their size. Box 10 also includes one folder of contact sheets from the 1990's. Each of these retains Adler's original number so that they can be correlated with any related photographic prints and the original enevelopes in which they were housed.
    The original envelopes have also been retained, and are housed in boxes 15-17. These envelopes contain handwritten notes and should be consulted for additional contextual information about the images.
    - Photographs, 1982-1989 (Offsite-box 11)
    - Photographs, 1990-2001 (Offsite-box 12)
    - Photographic Negatives, 1982-1986 (Offsite-box 13)
    - Photographic Negatives, 1987-1997 (Offsite-box 14)
    - Photographic Negatives, 1992-1997 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 11-12)
      These negatives are housed in negative sheets, and not individual envelopes.
    - Photo Contact Sheets, 1992-1997 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 13)
    - Original envelopes, 1981-1986 (Offsite-box 15)
    - Original envelopes, 1986-1991 (Offsite-box 16)
    - Original envelopes, 1991-1997 (Offsite-box 17)
- Series V: Peace Movement, 1963-1985
  This series contains correspondence, newsletters, articles, and fliers for the various Peace groups Cy Adler was affiliated with, including the War Resisters League and Performing Artists for Nuclear Disarmament (PAND).
  - Fund for Peace and War Resisters League, 1982-1985 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 8)
  - Nuclear War- Devastation and Facts, 1978-1982 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 9)
    Of note is Adler's essay, Prisoners of the Defense Myth: An Homage to Hiroshima.
  - Performing Artists for Nuclear Disarmament (PAND), 1963-1983 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 10)
    This folder also contains a flier for West Side Action for Peace and Social Justice.